Listen, everyone.
听着 大家
If you're not expected to pass this UTokyo practice exam,
这场东大模拟考 被我判定没有希望录取的人
you'll be made to quit the course.
我会叫他退出东大专科
-Huh? -What?
-啊？ -什么？
Hang on, sir!
等一下 老师！
-Does that mean we'd be kicked out? -What else would it mean?
-你的意思是我们可能会被踢走？ -要不然呢？
Sir, that's too harsh!
老师 这太严厉了！
I know I'd get an E if I did it now.
我现在考试的话肯定会得E
Yeah, there's no way!
对啊 根本不可能！
-What's an E? -Sir, I think that's harsh too.
-E是什么？ -老师 我也觉得太严厉了
Fujii, you're making sense for once.
藤井 你终于说人话了！
There will only be three of us left.
东大专科只会剩下我们三个人
What?! You lost to us twice and you say that?
什么？你输给我们两次还敢这么说？
-I never lost to you. -You piss me off, moody prick!
-我从来没输给你过 -你真是烦人 喜怒无常的混蛋
Stop, you two!
你们俩别吵了
Yeah, yeah. Shut up.
好了…闭嘴
Want to quit now?
你们现在就想退出吗？
I don't really get it, but I'll do it.
我不明白 但我会做
Seto. What are you saying?
濑户 你说什么？
Alright, it's decided.
好 那就决定了
Sir, can you start class already?
老师 你能开始教课了吗？
Aren't you being too strict?
你这样不会太严厉了吗？
At this point, only Kosugi and Fujii
这种情况下 只有小杉和藤井
and maybe Kenta could do it.
还有或许健太能做得到
Everyone else will get an E.
其他人都会考到E
They'll see where they stand.
他们会看清楚自己的程度
But you can't kick them out.
但你不能赶他们走
-Mr. Takahara! Tell him! -What?
-高原老师 快跟他说！ -什么？
It's not fair to kick out a student for a bad practice exam score.
因为学生考得不好 就把他们赶出去 这不公平
Huh? Is that what's happening?
什么？你们要这么做吗？
Is that a problem?
有什么问题吗？
With conditions like that, you could destroy their motivation.
你开出这种条件 可能会摧毁他们的动力
You should remove the condition.
你应该收回这条件
See?
你看吧
Pardon me.
失陪了
Mr. Takahara seems more passionate than usual.
高原老师看起来比平时热心
He cares for the students, unlike someone I know.
和我认识的某人不同 他很在乎学生
Because if five students don't pass, he can't become the chairman.
要是没有五位学生通过东大入学考 他就当不了理事长
He's so small-minded. Looking all smug and greedy like that.
他真是思想狭隘 看起来自以为是又贪婪
Yes, despite being vice principal.
对啊 区区一个教导主任
I see. So that's why.
原来是因为这样
But if less than five pass, you'll stay on as chairman.
但如果少过五位学生通过 你就能继续保住理事长的位置
Stay on?
继续保住？
What do you mean?
什么意思？
A silly bet with the former chairman.
和前任理事长的打赌
If you produce five successful students, Mr. Takahara becomes chairman.
要是你培养出五位东大生 高原老师就会当上理事长
And I am fired.
而我会被开除
What? We didn't know that.
什么？我们不知道这回事
Do you think you can get five kids into UTokyo?
你认为自己 能将五位学生送进东大吗？
I'm counting on you.
无论如何都要做到
That man…
那人…
I see. The former chairman wants you out at any cost.
原来前任理事长不惜代价想赶走你
-But why? -Why indeed!
-不过为什么呢？ -对啊 为什么呢？
That's not our problem.
无论如何 那不是我们的问题
Sorry, but all seven of my students will get into UTokyo.
不好意思 但我们七位学员都会考上东大
I can't change that goal.
我没办法改变这目标
Of course.
当然了
Alright, we're done here.
好 那今天就到这里吧
About the former chairman's plan to sell the school…
关于前任理事长要出售学校的事…
You don't plan on telling Mr. Sakuragi?
你没打算告诉樱木老师他们吗？
If all seven pass, it'll be my office's first big contract!
要是七人都通过了 这会是我事务所的第一单大合同！
Toranomon is not far off, right sir?
虎之门也就不远了 对吧老师？
It's time for you-know-who.
是时候请出那人了
Who?
谁？
Hayase, what's your problem?
早濑 你怎么回事？
-Huh? Do you understand? -What?
-咦？你明白吗？ -什么？
At this rate, you and I will get kicked out!
这样下去 我们俩都会被赶出专科！
-Yeah. -I'm going to complain!
-嗯 -我要去跟老师投诉！
-Stop that! -But I think we're really in trouble.
-别这样了！ -但我想我们真的麻烦大了
-Why? -A practice exam at this stage?
-为什么？ -现在这种阶段进行模拟考
Even top-class prep schools get mostly Es.
即使是一流的重点学校 也大多只会拿到E
-Yikes. -I told you!
-天啊 -我已经和你说了！
The only option is to listen to the teacher and work our butts off.
那唯一的选择 只有听老师的话拼命努力了
Huh? You can't be serious…
什么？你不是吧…
Following the teacher is the only way I know how to get into UTokyo.
听从老师的指示 是我唯一知道的考上东大的方法
Yeah, but…
话是这么说…
Maybe it's just a strategy to motivate us.
或许这只是一种激励我们的策略
Huh? Really?
咦？真的？
Yeah.
嗯
Right. I get it. That could be it.
我明白了 原来 也有这可能嘛
-Sheesh. -Dream on.
-什么啊 -继续发梦吧
Fujii, shut up.
藤井 闭嘴吧
Goodbye.
再见
-Kenta, let's go. -Okay.
-健太 走吧 -嗯
Kosugi's scary.
小杉好可怕
What should I do?
我该怎么办？
Don't worry, just do it.
别担心了 直接做吧
I know…
我知道…
But I hate this sort of pressure.
但我很讨厌这种压力
Kaede, don't you get nervous?
枫 你不会紧张吗？
Not compared to the national finals.
和全国大赛的决赛比起来 完全不会
I shouldn't have asked you. Yikes, yikes, yikes…
我不该问你的 糟了…
What am I gonna do?
我该怎么做？
You too?
你也这样吗？
Yikes! Yikes! Yikes!
糟了！
Yikes.
糟了…
Yikes, yikes… Yikes.
糟了…糟了啦！
I've always wondered, is that learning?
我总是在想 这算学习吗？
"Always"?
“总是”？
You can do what you want.
随你喜欢做什么
But if you're half-assing the UTokyo exam,
但你是不会通过东大模拟考的
you'll just embarrass yourself, so quit now.
你只会丢自己的脸 还是现在放弃吧
PRACTICE EXAM RESULTS YUTA AMANO
（模拟考成绩 天野裕太）
A…
A…
UTOKYO PRACTICE EXAM 8 DAYS TO GO
（东大模拟考 八天前）
What's this? It's hilarious!
这是什么？太好笑了！
So this was you-know-who, right?
这就是你说的那人 对吧？
What a colorful character.
真是有趣的个性
It's not a character, she's the real thing.
不只是个性 她可是很有实力的
Like this!
就像这样！
Huh? Like that?
什么？像这样？
Yeah!
对啊
Everyone try what I did!
大家试试看我刚刚的动作
Starting today until the practice exam,
听好了 今天起直到模拟考那天
you're going to train your ears well.
你们也得训练耳朵
I might be pretty good at listening.
我听力应该很好
Your ears alone seem alright.
濑户 你好的应该就只有听力了
Give me a break.
吵死了 偶尔就放过我吧
The English UTokyo entrance exam
东大入学试的英语考试
is one-quarter listening.
四分之一都是考听力
-One quarter? -Isn't that crazy?
-四分之一？ -这样不是很糟吗？
It's not crazy. If you can master listening,
一点都不糟 要是掌握了听力
your English marks will shoot up.
英文成绩就会飙升
So today I've invited a special instructor, Ms. Anna Yuri to come.
所以今天请了一位英语特别讲师 由利杏奈老师过来
People can't hear what they can't say.
人们无法听出他们不会说的语言
Even if you can't speak, listen to the audio and repeat it.
要是你不会说 就听音讯然后跟着念
This training is called "shadowing."
这叫“影子跟读法”
This is the best way to improve listening.
这是增强听力的最好方式
Seriously? Okay, I get that, but…
真的吗？我明白了 但是…
What?
什么？
Well, Ms. Anna Yuri was singing in such a quiet voice, I couldn't hear it.
由利杏奈老师唱得很小声 我听不见
Does that really help in learning English?
这对学英语真的有帮助吗？
It's okay! It's called "mumble shadowing."
没问题的！ 这叫“喃喃自语影子跟读法”
-Mumble shadowing? -Does mumbling do any good?
-喃喃自语影子跟读法？ -喃喃自语有什么帮助吗？
If you start out trying to speak loud and clear, you'll fail.
要是一开始就说得 大声而清晰 你会失败的
-Huh? -The first step to listening is mumbling.
-咦？ -练好听力的第一步是喃喃自语
What does that mean?
这是什么意思？
Someone who can't swim doesn't start with a perfect crawl.
不会游泳的人 并不能一开始就完美地爬泳
They first kick and adjust to the water.
他们会先踢水 慢慢适应水
-Oh. -It's just like that.
-哦 -就只是这样而已
But the key is don't try to be perfect.
关键是不要试图做到完美
Don't try?
不要试？
A lot of Japanese people have a perfectionist attitude toward language.
很多日本人对语言 有着完美主义的态度
What does "perfectionist" mean?
“完美主义”是什么意思？
For example, if someone asks you if you can speak English,
比如说 如果有人问你会不会说英语
Seto, how would you answer?
濑户 你会怎么回答？
Um… um…
呃…那个…
-Sorry, I picked the wrong student. -Hey!
-抱歉 我选错了人 -喂！
-Amano. -Huh?
-天野 -咦？
"I can not speak English well" or something?
“我英语说得不好”之类的？
Yes! Most people say that.
对！大多数人会这么说
Most Japanese people who are bad at English
大多数英语不好的日本人
answer just like Amano did.
会像天野一样回答
"I can not speak English well."
“我英语说得不好”
But if you ask an American sightseeing in Japan,
但要是你问来日本观光的美国人
"Can you speak Japanese?" How do you think they answer?
“你会说日语吗？” 你猜他们会怎么回答？
"I can speak Japanese very well."
“我日语说得很好”
"I like sushi and sumo! Ha ha ha!"
“我最喜欢寿司和相扑！哈哈哈！”
They answer with confidence.
他们会自信地回答
You don't have to try to be perfect.
你不需要做到完美
Speak with confidence.
自信地说话
That's the key to improving with languages.
这就是语言进步的关键
Amano, do it with confidence like you do on YouTube.
天野 拿出你做油管视频的自信
don't worry about mistakes, just mumble in a low voice.
别担心错误 小声地喃喃自语
Then, don't be shy, use your facial muscles
接着 别害羞 运用你的脸部肌肉
and say "I'm good at English." Speak with confidence.
说“我英语说得很好” 自信地说话
The key to doing well is don't try to be perfect and mimic.
说得好的关键是 不要试图变得完美 以及模仿
Mimic?
模仿？
Yes, mimic. Act it out!
是的 模仿 表现出来！
That sounds fun!
听起来很有趣！
This feels like a scam to me.
我听起来很可疑
Ma'am, maybe you just can't speak English.
老师 或许你不会说英语吧
-What did she say? -"Don't worry."
-她刚刚说了什么？ -“别担心”
"I can speak better than you. Stop complaining and study."
“我英语说得比你好 所以别抱怨了 快开始学吧”
"Cute little kid." That's what.
“可爱的孩子” 她说了这些
I'm sorry!
对不起！
Idiot!
笨蛋！
Okay, get mumble shadowing!
好 开始喃喃自语影子跟读吧
Okay!
是！
There's no other way to learn listening but to take time and get used to it!
听好了 训练听力的方法 就只有花时间慢慢习惯
Many test takers leave it to the last minute.
很多考生会把这拖到最后
The earlier you start, the bigger the benefit.
你越早开始 好处就越多
-Shall we go again? -Um.
-我们再来一次吧？ -嗯
What is it, Hayase?
怎么了 早濑？
Taking time to get used to it? I don't have that time right now.
花时间慢慢习惯？我现在没那时间
There's no time before the practice exam.
模拟考之前已经没有时间了
If I don't make it, I'll have to quit the Special Course.
如果我做不到 我就得退出专科
Hayase…
早濑…
It is fun, but there's no point to this!
这很有趣 但没有意义！
What, Hayase? You've already decided you'll be kicked out?
什么啊 早濑？ 你已经决定了要被踢出去吗？
That's not it exactly.
不是这样的
Red card.
红卡
Go take a hundred deep breaths outside. Get out!
去外面深呼吸一百次 出去
Hey, Mr. Sakuragi.
等一下 樱木老师
I hope Hayase is okay.
希望早濑没事
Wasn't making them quit based on results too strict?
依模拟考成绩来决定去留 不会太严格了吗？
-This is fine. -Huh?
-没问题的 -什么？
When people face high hurdles, their weaknesses are exposed.
当人面对困难的障碍时 他们的弱点就会暴露出来
Know your weaknesses, overcome them, and become stronger.
认识你的弱点 战胜它 变强
To pass, you need a strong heart.
要通过考试 得要有颗强大的心脏
That is true.
这是没错…
As long as they don't quit before they overcome it.
只要他们没在战胜之前退出
That's exactly when Hayase will give up.
这就是早濑会放弃的时候了
What?
什么？
-Here. -Mm.
-给 -嗯
Must be nice, Kenta.
健太 我好羡慕你哦
You have a reason to go to UTokyo.
你有上东大的理由
I'm kind of jealous.
我有点妒忌
I want to be like you.
我想像你一样
Always bright and smiling.
总是那么开朗 一直笑着
So cute.
真可爱
But you're not cute when you're down.
但你失落的时候不可爱
Yeah! It's a waste of my cuteness.
对啊！真是浪费了我的可爱
Yeah.
嗯
Thanks, Kenta.
谢谢你 健太
I get it, too.
我也明白
I know I have to work harder.
我应该更努力
-What are you doing, Kenta? -Mari!
-你在干嘛 健太？ -麻里！
If you've got time to worry, you might as well study.
早濑 你有时间担心 还不如去学习
-Let's go back. -Okay.
-回去吧 -嗯
I get it! I know!
我明白的！我知道！
Have confidence.
要有自信
Hey.
嘿
-Fujii. -How about that practice exam.
-藤井 -模拟考怎么样了？
I guess you don't want an E. You'd have to quit.
你应该不想拿E吧？这样你就得退出
I don't know if I can get an A, but I want at least a B.
我也不知道能不能拿A 但我至少也想拿B吧
Oof.
哎呀
I heard your little brother goes to Reimeikan High School
我听说你弟弟在黎明馆高中上学
and is aiming for UTokyo.
目标也是东大
Yeah, so what?
是啊 那又怎样？
I get it. Having a smart brother, but being, you know.
我明白的 有位聪明的兄弟而自己却…你知道的
-What's that supposed to mean? -Chill out!
-那是什么意思？ -放松！
Anyway, you sure caught that teacher's English well.
对了 亏你把那老师的英语都听懂了
One week until the practice exam.
距离模拟考还有一周
I'll tell you something useful. Six Rules for the UTokyo Practice Exam.
我会给你们一些有用的建议 东大模拟考六大规则
Number one.
一
Take the practice exam six times.
做六次模拟考
-Six times? -Yes.
-六次？ -是
The UTokyo practice exam
东大模拟考
is held over ten times per year. Take at least six of those.
一年会举办十次 至少参加其中六次
Listen. The UTokyo practice exam is really long.
听着 东大模拟考用时很长
It's common for some subjects to take more than two hours.
有些科目用时两小时以上 这很常见
It requires mental and physical strength.
所以这需要你们精神和身体的耐力
Taking it six times will help your body adjust.
练习六次 能让身体习惯上
I'm tired just thinking about it.
我想到就觉得累
Number two. Start the literature exam from the classical section.
二 语文考试从古文部分答起
Never start the literature exam from the beginning.
语文考试中 不要从试卷的开始答起
Why?
为什么？
What do you have to watch out for most during an exam? Fujii.
考试时最该注意什么 藤井？
Managing your health.
保持健康
That's important too. Kosugi?
那也很重要 小杉？
-Time allocation. -Right.
-时间分配 -对
The key to success is how efficiently you can answer questions.
成功的关键是你回答问题的效率
Solve the problems you can do and get points.
答你能解的题以获取分数
That's classical literature.
那就是古文
Listen. The modern literature in the UTokyo exam is very tough.
听着 东大考试的现代文部分很难
Compared to that, classics and kanji texts include
和那比起来 古文和汉字部分的
simple translation problems and it's easy to get points.
翻译题更简单 更容易让你拿到分数
If you start with modern lit, you'll get bogged down.
要是从现代文开始 你会被拖慢
You'll run out of time for the easy classics and panic.
你会没时间去做 简单的古文题 然后开始慌张
Start the literature exam with the classical section.
语文考试从古文部分答起
Lit from the classics!
语文从古文做起！
Number three.
三
For math, write out your plan.
数学考试中 将你的计划写出来
What does that mean?
那是什么意思？
Like modern literature, UTokyo math is wildly difficult.
和现代文一样 东大考试的数学极为困难
Some of you here
你们之中的一些人
will find it impossible to write the formulas and answers.
会发现自己没法写出公式和答案
But what if you write nothing?
但要是你什么都不写的话呢？
What? You get zero.
什么？你会得零分
Yes. So you write your strategy.
是的 所以将你的策略写出来
Show how you would solve the problem.
展示自己解决问题的方法
Write your thinking. Then you can get some points.
写下你的思考过程 那你就会获得一些分数
But is that okay?
但这没问题吗？
The thing about UTokyo math
东大考试的数学试卷中
is they mark partial answers.
他们会批改不完整的答案
If they can see you could solve it, they recognize that.
要是他们认为你能解决问题 他们就会承认这一点
Even if you can't write a single formula,
即使你不能写出某个公式
you could still get some points.
你还是能获得一些分数
-Seriously? -Just write something.
-真的吗？ -写些什么就对了
That's the rule for UTokyo math.
这就是东大数学的规则
Number four, Mizuno.
四 水野
Number four. Always bring snacks.
四 一定要带零食
ALWAYS BRING SNACKS
（一定要带零食）
What's with that?
这是什么啊？
Seto, if you mock snacks, you'll fail.
濑户 要是你小看零食 你可是会落榜的
Seriously?
认真的吗？
The UTokyo exam lasts from 9:00 a.m. to 7:20 p.m.
东大考试从早上9点 考到晚上7点20分
The liberal arts literature exam is two and a half hours.
文学考试历时两小时半
-Two and a half hours?! -It's an endurance test.
-两小时半？ -这是体力竞赛
So you need snacks.
所以你们一定要零食
You will need an energy supply on your breaks.
你们需要在小休时补充能量
By bringing things you like,
带自己喜欢的食物
you can also refresh yourself.
也能让你打起精神
-Makes sense. -Ma'am!
-有道理 -我有问题！
-Kosugi. -How much can we bring?
-小杉 -我们可以带多少呢？
-It's not a field trip. -It's up to you.
-又不是出去野餐 -这要看你
-Bring however much you want. -Okay.
-你想带多少就带多少 -明白了
Number five.
五
Social studies will only have what you've learned.
社会科目只会出你学过的范围
What we've learned?
学过的范围？
They only include what you've studied.
他们只会出你学过的知识
The June practice exam doesn't include the modern era.
六月的模拟考不包含近代内容
Don't study extra.
不用花时间学那些
Finally, English.
最后 英语
Number six. Don't take notes during listening.
六 听的时候不要做笔记
Everyone, look at the English test paper I've handed out.
大家 看看我刚刚发的英语试卷
"You may take notes while listening."
“你可以边听边做笔记”
So you can take notes.
所以我们能做笔记
Look carefully. It says you may take notes.
小心看好了 它说你“可以”做笔记
I don't get it.
我不明白
It's better to write what you hear.
把你听到的写下来做笔记更好吧
No, that's a trap.
不 那是陷阱
-Huh? -Do you all like conveyor belt sushi?
-咦？ -大家爱吃回转寿司吗？
-I love sushi.
-什么？ -我爱寿司！
-It's the same. -No, no.
-那是一样的 -不
-I still don't get it. -You're dumb as usual.
-我还是不明白 -你还是一样迟钝 坏男孩！
English is like sushi flowing by on a conveyor belt.
英语就像在回转带上流动的寿司
If you try to take notes,
要是试图用做笔记来抓重点
you'll get distracted by the notes
反而会被笔记干扰
and you could miss hearing something important.
并可能漏听重要的内容
Then they shouldn't say "You may take notes."
那他们不该说“你可以做笔记”
A trap set by UTokyo!
东大设的陷阱！
You fell right into it.
而你掉进去了
Enough from you. I won't get trapped now.
真啰嗦 我不会再掉进去了
One more important thing.
还有一件重要的事
Check the questions and explanations before the listening begins.
在听之前 查看问题和解说
You can predict what sort of things you'll hear.
你就能预测自己将听到什么内容了
It'll be much easier to remember.
这样一来就会更容易记住
Alright! That was good advice.
好！那真是个好建议
That's right, Seto. It makes a big difference if you know this stuff.
没错 濑户 能不能预想内容会有很大不同
Use this information when you take the exam.
挑战东大考试一定要活用所有情报
-You're all very lucky. -Really?
-你们都很幸运 -真的？
-Wow. -Lucky! Lucky!
-耶 -幸运！
-Okay. -Keep this all in mind.
-真好 -把这些都记住了
And use all you've got to put your energy into the test!
把你们现在拥有的 全部投入到考试中吧！
UTOKYO PRACTICE EXAM THE DAY BEFORE
（东大模拟考 一天前）
-Goodbye, take care! -Goodbye!
-再见 保重！ -再见！
Fujii.
藤井
Tomorrow's the UTokyo practice exam. Good luck!
明天就是东大模拟考了 加油！
Thanks.
好
Huh?
咦？
Amano, Hayase.
天野 早濑
Good luck on the test tomorrow!
明天的考试加油！
Yes, sir!
是！
I'll try my best.
我会加油的
Hey, do you think everything's okay?
我说 你觉得一切会没事吗？
The test is tomorrow. I'm nervous.
明天就是考试了 我好紧张
Not you. Nao.
我不是说你 我说早濑
Huh?
什么？
She's been acting weird lately.
她今天举止很奇怪
Yeah, Amano is too.
对啊 天野也是
But we're in no position to worry about them.
但我们顾不上担心他们了
I can't get kicked out.
我绝对不能被踢出去
Me too.
我也是
…until discovery, was the largest insect in Japan.
…被发现之前 是全日本体型最大的昆虫
Hey, the UTokyo practice exam is tomorrow! You're relaxed.
喂！明天是东大模拟考了 你真轻松
-Seto, it's a rhinoceros beetle! Look. -Huh?
-濑户 这是犀牛甲虫 你看 -什么？
That's a cool one.
这看起来好厉害啊
Iwasaki, what snacks are you bringing?
岩崎 你会带什么零食？
Snacks?
零食？
Can you teach me some conditioning methods for game day?
你能教我一些比赛时的调适方法吗？
"Game day"?
“比赛”？
Oh, I see.
哦 这样啊
A practice exam is a game.
模拟考也是一场比赛
The real one is next year. Tomorrow is just a practice match.
正式的在明年 明天只是预赛
We can only output what we've learned.
虽然也只能尽目前的能力去考
-Yeah. -Right.
-嗯 -很好
Let's work on vocabulary until the last minute.
直到最后一分钟前 来学单词吧
-Okay. -Hey, Kenta, watch this.
-好 -好 健太 看这
-Yeah. -Here we go.
-来 -开始啦
Magical exam.
神奇考试
You say exam, I say literature.
你说考试 我说语文
You say literature, I say classics.
你说语文 我说古文
You say classics, I say The Pillow Book.
你说古文 我说《枕草子》
You say The Pillow Book, I say Sei Shonagon.
你说《枕草子》 我说清少纳言
-Huh? Hang on… -Kaede, you lose!
-咦？等一下… -枫 你输了！
Seto, I never thought you'd say Sei Shonagon.
濑户 我没想到你会说清少纳言
Seto, that's great!
濑户真厉害！
UTOKYO PRACTICE EXAM DAY
（东大模拟考 当天）
Hey, Amano.
嘿 天野
Fujii.
藤井
You look pale. Are you scared?
你怎么那么苍白？很害怕吗？
You can't get a good score with that attitude!
靠这状态 你可没办法考到好分数
Even if you get kicked out, I'll teach you.
就算你被东大专科赶出去 我也可以教你
How can you be so insensitive?
你怎么可以那么没眼力见？
I don't have your confidence.
我没有你的自信
I want to concentrate. Don't talk to me.
我想专注 别跟我说话
The cosθ question on the old exam
过往考试那道cosθ的题
was super easy to solve with an αβ inequal formula.
用αβ不等式公式来解就会很简单
Oh no, I'm super nervous.
糟了 我好紧张
Morning, Nao!
早 菜绪！
-Good morning! -You're so nervous!
-早上好！ -你也太紧张了吧
Relax, relax!
放松点！
Even if you're kicked out, you won't die.
就算被提出专科 你也不会死的
Nao, let's go.
菜绪 走吧
Everyone looks so smart.
大家都看起来好聪明
I'm the dumbest one here, I know it.
我是这里最笨的那个 我知道的
Ah, it's Kosugi.
是小杉
Mari! Seto! Iwasaki!
麻里！濑户！岩崎！
Who's he? He's kind of weird.
那人是谁啊？他看起来好奇怪
-Noisy. -Excuse me?
-吵死了 -什么？
Kenta, sit down.
健太 坐下来
Okay.
嗯
FIRST SUBJECT - LITERATURE
（第一科 语文）
Will everyone here get into UTokyo?
这里的所有人都会考进东大吗？
Alright, please begin.
好 请开始
Ugh. It's all essay questions.
全都是论述题
There's no way I can do this!
我不可能做到！
Whoa. Kosugi's writing something already.
糟了 小杉已经开始写些什么了
What should I do?
我该怎么办？
UTokyo Practice Exam Rule Two.
东大模拟考规则二
Start the lit exam with the classical section.
语文考试从古文部分答起
What should I do? I don't know anything.
我该做什么？我什么都不会
I thought the classics had the easy questions…
不是说古文部分 绝对可以拿到分数吗？
Wow, everyone's writing answers.
太厉害了 大家都在答题
Yikes, yikes, yikes.
糟糕
SECOND SUBJECT - MATH
（第二科 数学）
Whoa, what is this?
这是什么？
I don't know how to solve these!
我不知道怎么解！
What is this? It's impossible!
这是什么？做不到！
Whatever. I'll just write some strategies.
随便了 我写下我的答题策略好了
LUNCH BREAK
（午休）
Nao, how was it?
菜绪 怎么样？
Terrible. I'm kicked out for sure.
真的很糟糕 我一定会被踢出去
I did awful too.
我也答得不好
Hayase, do you want to eat lunch with us?
早濑 要和我们一起吃午餐吗？
Sorry, I'm not hungry at all.
抱歉 我完全不饿
-Okay. -Well, good luck this afternoon.
-好 -那 今天下午加油
Yeah.
嗯
Yikes, yikes, yikes.
糟了
Huh?
什么？
How can they eat so much at a time like this?
这种时候他们还能吃那么多？
This isn't an eating contest!
这又不是大胃王比赛！
Everyone's powerful.
大家都好强
UTokyo might be impossible for me.
东大对我来说应该是不可能的了
It's totally impossible.
绝对不可能
Sir, how long do you plan to sleep?
老师 你打算睡多久？
Everyone's at their practice test.
大家都在为东大模拟考努力着
Get up, sir!
老师 起来了！
Shut up.
闭嘴
No. Get up!
不 起来！
Hey! Hang on!
喂！等一下！
I can't do this…
我做不到…
Who is that YouTuber?
那个油管博主是谁？
He raps in English with an afro and sunglasses.
他戴爆炸头假发和墨镜 用英语饶舌
That's hilarious. A wildman.
真滑稽 是个野人
Yeah, I got hooked on him. He's super funny.
对啊 我被他迷住了 他超级搞笑
Really? I'll check him out.
真的吗？我待会看看
He's taking the practice exam.
他也来模拟考了
-I guess he's here somewhere? -I'd freak if I saw him.
-我想他在附近吧 -如果见到他 我会特别兴奋
-For sure. -Yeah.
-对啊 -嗯
That's me!
那是我！
-Hang on! -Seriously.
-等一下 -说真的
How can you sleep at a time like this?
你怎么能在这种时候睡觉？
Why all the fuss? They're the ones taking the test.
干嘛那么大小怪？考试的人是他们
I mean, yes, but…
话是这么说 但…
I'm worried. I just hope they don't get overwhelmed.
我很担心 希望他们不会承受不住
They'll face the real exam alone. They have to work it out themselves.
他们会独自面对真正的考试 他们得自己解决
You're right.
你说得对
They must believe in what they've done. They must respect themselves.
他们得相信自己付出的努力 得肯定自己的能力
If they can do that, they can regain their innate strength.
若能做到这点 他们就能找回原本的实力
But if they can't…
但要是不能…
100,000 VIEWS!
（达到十万观看次数！）
100,000 VIEWS
（第58天 东大模拟考！ 十万观看次数）
My viewers are skyrocketing.
我的观看人数正在飙升
I'M ALSO SHOOTING FOR UTOKYO.
（我也在努力上东大）
YEAH! LET'S DO IT!
（耶！一起加油！）
Other exam takers are watching.
其他考生都在看
Alright!
好！
THIRD SUBJECT - ENGLISH (READING)
（第三科 英语阅读）
The English essay.
英语论述题
Write down what you think about these illustrations.
写下你对这些插图的看法
It's what I always do.
这是我平常都在做的
THIRD SUBJECT - ENGLISH (LISTENING)
（第三科 英语听力）
What is everyone writing?
大家都在写什么？
Hang on.
等一下
Conveyor belt sushi. Don't take notes.
回转寿司 不要写笔记
English is like sushi flowing by on a conveyor belt.
英语就像在回转带上的流动的寿司
If you try to take notes,
要是试图用做笔记来抓重点
you'll get distracted
反而会被笔记干扰
and you could miss something important.
并可能漏听重要的内容
Focus on listening.
专心听
Focus…
专注…
I understand. I can catch most of what's being said.
我明白了 我能听懂大部分的内容
Pencils down.
考试结束
It's over.
结束了
Fujii.
藤井
I'm sorry about this morning. I just couldn't…
今早的事很抱歉 我当时没有…
Hayase.
早濑
How was it?
怎么样？
Oh, um, okay I guess.
哦 嗯 应该还可以
How about you?
你呢？
It was harder than I expected.
比我预期的还要难
But it was a good experience.
不过是个好经验
Okay, see you tomorrow.
那么明天见
Bye.
再见
Yeah, bye.
嗯 再见
Sakamoto, we'll also be present at the next meeting.
坂本先生 我们会出席下次会议
And here's that document you wanted.
这是你要的文件
Oh. Thank you.
哦 谢谢
Finally Mr. Sakuragi is involved.
樱木老师终于参与进来了
Do you think he'll really get five students in?
你认为他真能将五位学生送进去吗？
It'll be a problem if he doesn't.
要是他做不到 就有麻烦了
Yes, it will.
是啊
TATSUMI GAKUEN SURVEY DOCUMENTS CONCERNING SALE
（龙海学园出售调查资料）
UTOKYO PRACTICE EXAM THE NEXT DAY
（东大模拟考 隔天）
How was it? The UTokyo practice exam.
东大模拟考 你们做得怎么样？
Honestly, it was so hard I don't know how I did.
老实说 太难了 难到我不知道我表现得怎么样
I was no match for it.
我不是它的对手
Yeah, but…
是啊 但是…
What?
什么？
I did all I could.
我尽全力了
Yeah, I used everything I know.
嗯 我用尽了自己知道的所有知识
Amano?
天野呢？
At first, I did terribly.
一开始我答得很差
But I started to feel better after lunch.
但午餐过后我的状态开始改善
So I think I tried my best.
我想我也尽力了
Kenta?
健太呢？
It was fun.
很有趣
A very Kenta answer.
真是典型的健太
Kosugi, how was it?
小杉 怎么样？
How did it go…?
怎么样…
I guess it was fun for me too.
我想对我来说也很有趣
Fun? You two are amazing. Kenta and Kosugi.
有趣？你们俩真厉害 健太和小杉
Before, I wasn't even allowed to study.
在这之前 我甚至不被允许学习
But now I can put all my effort into studying for UTokyo.
但现在我能全力以赴为东大学习
Fujii?
藤井呢？
Piece of cake.
小菜一碟
I see.
这样啊
Hayase, how about you?
早濑 你呢？
Me?
我？
It was terrible.
完全做不了
It felt so long.
我觉得时间过得好慢
I don't even like thinking about it.
我连想都不愿意想
Surrounded by pressure.
被压力包围着
Like, "So these are the people who will take the UTokyo exam."
“所以这些就是会 参加东大入学试的人啊”
I started to think it was impossible.
我开始想 我没办法做到
So…
所以…
So you'll drop out of the exam?
所以你不要考东大入学试了？
You're saying you want to quit trying for UTokyo?
你的意思是 你要放弃考东大？
If my practice exam results are bad,
要是我模拟考的成绩很差
I have to quit, don't I?
我就得退出 对吧？
Then I have no way to get into UTokyo.
那我就不可能进东大了
I know without seeing the results.
我不用看成绩就能知道
I'm quitting. Thanks for everything.
我要退出 一直以来谢谢你们
-Hey, Nao. -Iwasaki.
-等一下 菜绪 -岩崎
-But… -Leave her.
-但是… -让她去吧
Sir, are you sure?
老师 你确定吗？
What am I doing?
我在干嘛？
Hey, Hayase.
喂 早濑
Huh? What?
咦？什么？
We heard you were feeling down.
我们听说你心情不好
-From who? -Well…
-谁说的？ -这个嘛…
It's great to work towards a goal.
有一个目标并为之努力 真好
Isn't that what youth is all about?
这不就是青春的意义吗？
Studying like mad.
疯狂地学习
You can only do that now. Right?
只有现在才能这么做 对吧？
Yeah, when I graduate,
对啊 我毕业后
I'm supposed to take over the family business.
应该要继承家族生意
I'd rather go to Keio University.
我更想去庆应大学
Compared to that, your situation is better.
和那比起来 你的情况还好点
What are you trying to say? Leave me alone.
你们想说什么？别烦我了
Hey, hey, c'mon.
嘿 喂！
Trust Mr. Sakuragi and give it a try.
相信樱木老师 试试看吧
He's a pretty good guy.
他是个蛮好的人
-If you need anything, say so. -See you!
-你需要什么就跟我们说 -再见！
Sir!
老师！
What is it?
什么事？
Hayase still hasn't gotten home.
早濑还没回家
It's only 8 p.m.
现在才八点
Don't go to sleep! Let's go find her!
别睡了 去找她吧！
-Aren't you worried? -She'll be getting hungry soon.
-你不担心吗？ -她很快就会饿了
If you offer to buy her dinner, she'll come.
要是你请她吃晚饭 她会来的
Surely she wouldn't fall for that.
她才不会吃这一套
Idiot. Most worries are solved by a meal and a night's sleep.
笨蛋 大多数的烦恼 只要吃一餐和睡一觉就能解决
-Yeah, but… -Hey!
-是没错 但是… -喂！
Come back! You're smarter than me, so be confident!
回来吧！你比我还要聪明 自信点！
You've worked so hard up to now.
你一直都那么努力
Keep fighting a little longer.
再坚持一下
Anyway, I want to study with you!
而且 我想和你一起学习
It's always sunny above the clouds.
云的上方总是阳光明媚
I know I have to work hard.
我也知道我该努力
Are you hungry? Let's meet at Setoya!
你饿了吗？在濑户家见吧
I won't fall for that.
我才不吃这一套
Sir, you just wanted to eat.
老师 你是自己想吃饭了吧
I'm hungry. I can't help it.
我饿了 没办法
Right, Seto?
对吧 濑户？
Welcome.
欢迎光临
-Hayase. -Hey, Hayase.
-早濑 -哦 早濑
Want some ramen?
要吃拉面吗？
Sis, one ramen.
姊 一碗拉面
-Okay! -Your mom was worried.
-好！ -你妈妈很担心你
C'mon, sir.
来 老师
You've got a good family.
你有个好家庭
If their daughter isn't home by eight,
女儿八点还没回到家
most don't worry that much.
多数人都不会那么担心
You think?
是吗？
I don't know about other families.
我不太清楚其他家庭怎么样
Seems like they let you take a lot of lessons.
看来他们让你参加很多兴趣班
Piano, dance, swimming, calligraphy.
钢琴、舞蹈、游泳、书法
You tried them all and then quit.
你都试过 然后退出了
That's got nothing to do with this.
那和这没关系
Is trying for UTokyo like those lessons?
东大和这些兴趣班一样吗？
Are you giving up that easily?
你要那么轻易放弃吗？
Hayase.
早濑
You were born lucky.
你很幸运
Lucky? I'm just normal.
幸运？我很普通
I have a normal home and normal parents. I just go to school.
我有个普通的家庭 普通的父母 我天天也只是上学而已
I'm saying that normal is lucky.
我的意思是 能普通就很幸运了
Look at everyone.
你看每个人
They all have a burden.
他们身上都有包袱
Can you still say you're not happy?
你还能说自己不幸福吗？
What are you trying to say?
你想说什么？
Hayase. If you keep this up,
早濑 如果你继续这样下去
you'll lose that luck.
你会失去这份运气
Lose my luck?
失去运气？
I'm lucky, aren't I? You're saying something else.
我很幸运不是吗？ 你怎么说相反的话？
You don't realize you're lucky. People like that
你没意识到自己很幸运 这样的人
they lead an unlucky life. That's what I'm saying.
会过上不幸的人生 我是这个意思
What? I don't understand.
什么？我不明白
You do. People who don't know they're lucky
你明白的 那些不知道自己幸运的人
can't be satisfied with what they have and keep chasing something.
无法满足现状 不断追逐更多
But without conviction.
却缺乏信念
So they quit when it gets tough.
所以当事情变得困难 他们就会放弃
On to the next, and the next. Without lasting.
然后转移到另一件事 再另一件事 无法坚持下去
One after another, provided with things thanks to luck.
一件接着一件 运气提供你各种条件
It weakens your conviction.
削弱你的信念
People like that,
这样的人
do you think they can be happy?
你认为他们能幸福吗？
You're getting intimidated by Kosugi, no?
你被小杉吓到了 对吧？
-Why? -I can tell by looking at you.
-什么？ -我看着你就知道了
Kosugi is Kosugi. You are you.
小杉是小杉 你是你
If you have the conviction to get into UTokyo,
要是你有绝对要上东大的信念
you won't be bothered by others.
你不会被其他人影响
If you want to be happy, get some conviction.
要是你想变得幸福 去寻找信念吧
But..
但是
I have to quit the Special Course, right?
我必须退出东大专科 对吧？
The practice exam results aren't out yet.
模拟考的成绩还没出来
I know that.
我知道的
But I know I got an E.
我知道我会得E
You know what an E means?
你知道E是什么意思吗？
You have a 20% chance of passing.
你有五分之一的可能会通过考试
If you take the exam 100 times,
要是你考100次试
you'll be able to pass 20 times.
你会有20次是可以通过的
You were born lucky. Luck is on your side.
你天生就很幸运 运气站在你这边
You could get one of those twenty times.
这次可能是那20次的其中一次
That's just relying on luck.
那只是在依靠运气
Luck is important with entrance exams. But if you don't try,
运气对入学试来说很重要 但如果你连试都不试
you can't use your luck. Use it or throw it away.
你就没法用上你的运气 要么用它 要么把它丢掉
It's your choice.
由你来选择
Listen, Hayase.
听着 早濑
If you don't want to waste your life,
如果你不想浪费你的人生
use your luck.
使用你的运气吧
Thanks for waiting. Extra pork.
久等了 给你加了叉烧
Eat up.
吃吧
Thanks.
我开动了
Okay, we're starting.
好 我们开始了
SEVERAL WEEKS LATER
（数周后）
Finally, the UTokyo practice exam results.
东大模拟考的成绩终于出来了
Mizuno.
水野
You all remember our promise.
你们还记得我们的约定吧
Depending on the exam results, you'll have to quit the Special Course.
根据考试成绩 可能有人得退出专科
I'll announce it.
我现在开始宣布
Kosugi.
小杉
You got an A.
你考到A
-You nailed it. -Truly.
-你表现得很好 -真的
At this stage, an A is amazing.
这阶段能拿A实在是很了不起
Kenta.
健太
You got a C.
你拿到C
-Is a C good? -Very good.
-C算好吗？ -很好
But the differences between subjects are too wide.
但每科的成绩差距太大了
-Work on your weak points. -Okay.
-要改善你的弱点 -嗯
You got a better math score than me.
你的数学比我还要高分
A better score than Mari!
比麻里还要高分！
Fujii.
藤井
You got a D.
你拿到D
Overcoming your weak subjects is your new goal.
你的新目标是克服你的弱点
And Seto,
还有濑户
Iwasaki, Amano,
岩崎 天野
and Hayase.
和早濑
You all got Es.
你们都拿到E
An E…
E吗…
I knew it wouldn't be easy.
我就知道没那么容易
Well yeah, of course.
也是 当然了
What'll happen to us?
我们会怎么样？
We have to quit the Special Course, right?
我们得退出专科 对吗？
Huh?
什么？
Why are you laughing?
你怎么在笑？
-You should laugh too. -Huh?
-你也该笑 -什么？
Go on, laugh! When you fail, you laugh!
笑啊！失败的时候就笑吧！
Look.
看吧
Go on, laugh.
继续 笑吧
Go on.
来吧
Yeah, that's it.
嗯 就是这样
Yes, when you fail, you should laugh.
就是这样 失败的时候就笑吧！
What matters is what you do next.
重要的是 接下来该怎么做
Next? What do you mean?
接下来？什么意思？
Work hard at something else?
在其它地方努力？
I'll ask you this.
我来问你
With these practice exam results,
以模拟考的成绩
did you want to quit trying for UTokyo?
你们想要放弃考东大吗？
Of course not.
当然不了
We can't give up now.
我们不能现在放弃
Even if it takes years, I'll try.
即使要花个几年 我也会继续试
Hayase.
早濑
How about you?
你呢？
I have good luck. Even if I get kicked out,
我有运气 就算我被踢出专科
I'll never, never give up!
我也绝对…不会放弃！
The results of this exam
这次考试的成绩
are just your current abilities.
只是代表你们现在的能力
If you can face these results
要是你们能面对这些成绩
and you still want to go to UTokyo,
还想上东大的话
you have a chance of passing.
你们就有通过的可能
What do you mean? I don't get it.
这是什么意思？我不明白
Even if we got an E, we don't have to quit?
即使我们拿到了E 也不用退出吗？
I never said I'd kick you out if you got an E.
我从来没说过 拿到E就把你们踢出去的话
I said people who are not expected to pass.
我说的是那些没有希望录取的人
Hayase just misunderstood.
早濑误会了
-Hey. -Huh?
-真是的 -什么？
-Nao! -What!
-菜绪！ -什么啊！
-Heh. -Don't give us "heh."
-哈哈 -别给我“哈哈”
Anyway, let me tell you something.
顺带一提 我告诉你们件好事
If you get an E, it doesn't mean you're in the bottom 20%.
拿到E不代表 你们是考生中最差的五分之一
It doesn't?
不代表吗？
It depends on the exam, but grades A through D are about 50%.
视考试而定 但A到D占了总数一半
In this case, about half of test takers
这次的情况 大约一半的考生
got Es.
都考到了E
Really?
真的吗？
That means if we get a D, we're in the top half?
也就是说即使得了D 我们还是优秀的那一半？
-That's right. -Whoa!
-没错 -哇！
Especially Hayase, your grades were closest to the D line.
特别是早濑 你的成绩最接近D的分数线
You do have good luck.
你真的很幸运
-Really? -Yes, really.
-真的？ -是真的
When I took my first UTokyo practice exam, I also got an E.
我第一次考东大模拟考时也得了E
-You did? -Yes.
-老师你也是？ -是啊
But at this stage, don't worry about Es.
但这阶段得到E别担心
This is the best time for that. Think of yourself as lucky.
现在是最适合考到E的时候了 想想自己有多幸运
-Oh, we're lucky! -Lucky!
-对啊 我们真幸运！ -幸运！
Listen, studying is like an airplane.
听着 学习就像飞机一样
An airplane?
飞机？
In order for it to fly, it has to go down a runway.
飞机要飞起来之前 必须先驶过跑道
It runs and builds up buoyancy until it floats.
它持续地跑 累积浮力 直到飞起来
Then it ascends rapidly.
然后迅速上升
You all will build up your power and your time to fly will come.
你们慢慢积攒能量 飞行的时机最终就会来
The real battle starts now.
真正的战斗现在才开始
Alright, let's do this!
好 加油吧！
-Let's power through! -Yeah!
-猛踩油门吧！ -好！
-Power through! -Yeah Kenta, power through!
-踩油门！ -是啊 健太 踩油门吧！
-You idiot!
-你这个笨蛋！
-I'm sorry! -Sheesh!
-对不起！ -真是
-That's great. -Isn't it? Lucky!
-真好 -不是吗？幸运！
Lucky!
幸运！
Shit. Why?
该死 为什么？
Are you disappointed with your D?
你对自己的D很失望吗？
Shut up.
吵死了
You thought it couldn't happen?
你以为这不可能发生吗？
Don't forget this feeling.
别忘记这感觉
This is bullshit.
胡说八道
You're so mad you're crying?
你气哭了？
Never forget that.
别忘记了
Shut up.
吵死了
I'll leave the rest to you.
剩下的交给你了
Thank you.
谢谢
Sorry about before.
之前的事对不起
I was at my limit.
我那时在崩溃边缘
Shut up. Don't look at me.
吵死了 别看着我
Don't say that.
别这么说
I got an E!
我拿到了E！
-You laughed. -I did.
-你笑了 -对啊
-Hey. -I've never seen an E before.
-喂 -我从来没看过E
You never planned on kicking anyone out.
你从来没想把谁踢出去
Of course not. Our goal is to
当然不 我们的目标是
get more than five students into UTokyo.
将五个以上的学生送进东大
If even one quits, we're upping the risk.
即使是有一位退出 我们的风险也会增加
Exactly. All seven could pass!
没错 搞不好七位都会通过！
-Another order of gyoza please! -Yes ma'am.
-再来一盘饺子！ -是
-Here. -Thanks!
-给 -谢谢
Anyway, the UTokyo Special Course is on track.
无论如何 东大专科上轨道了
The two top students joined and there are seven now.
加入了全校前两名的学生 现在一共有七位学员
Anyway, five people need to get into UTokyo.
无论如何 必须要有五位进入东大
As long as they achieve that,
只要他们能做到
I'll have no other use for Sakuragi and the rest.
樱木他们对我就没有利用价值了
If five pass, we can remove the chairman.
要是五位通过了 我们就能除掉理事长
My daughter's the only one opposed to the sale.
我女儿是唯一一个反对出售的人
Will the vice principal in line to be chairman be okay?
那个等着要当 理事长的教导主任会同意吗？
That man won't be hard to deal with.
对付那人不难
-I see. -And? How's the situation?
-这样啊 -所以呢？情况怎么样？
Mr. Matsubara?
松原先生？
The commercial land around Tatsumi
围绕龙海学园的商业用地
is already in our hands.
已经在我们手中
All that's left is Tatsumi.
只剩龙海学园了
Can you really make such bold moves?
你真的能做出那么大胆的举动？
Of course, to avoid detection,
当然了 为了避免被发现
we've concealed the land information.
我们隐藏了土地的信息
There's no chance of a leak.
根本没有泄露的可能
You've got great employees.
你有很厉害的员工呢
You're all from UTokyo,
你们都是东大毕业生
but you're not like my daughter.
但和我女儿一点都不像
-Very talented. -No.
-真是优秀 -不
Once you're in society,
一旦踏入社会
academic background means nothing.
学历就不代表什么了
ABOUT THE PLAN TO SELL TATSUMI GAKUEN
（龙海学园出售计划）
Sir?
老师？
I never want an ugly score like that again.
我再也不想考出这种烂成绩了
Aim higher than E.
目标是摆脱E
We have another special instructor.
今天我请来一位特别讲师
Huh?
什么？
We're not at a level to teach!
我们才不是能教学的水平！
Will you train with us?
你能和我们一起训练吗？
Please allow her to join.
请务必让她加入
It's a month of solid practice.
那是为期一个月的扎实训练
A month?
一个月？
Focus, focus!
专注啊专注！
Devise the fastest and most certain strategy.
制定一个最快、最可靠的策略
In other words, know your distance from UTokyo.
换句话说 看清你和东大之间的距离
Subtitle translation by: Claire Tanaka
字幕翻译：赵慈宇